A Guide to the Christiansburg [Virginia] Industiral Institute Historical Documents, 1866-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Christiansburg [Virginia] Industrial Institute Historical Documents 1866-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms1991-033
0.4 cubic feet, 1 box, 11 folders
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Alternate Form Available
Virginia Tech's Imagebase contains more than 1200 digital images from the Christiansburg Industrial Institute Historical Documents. Images include scrapbooks and yearbooks, magazine and newspaper articles, and annual reports.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Christiansburg Industrial Institute (CII) was founded in 1866 in Cambria (now Christiansburg), Virginia, by Civil War Union Captain Charles S. Shaeffer as a private primary school for black children. Through the support of the Friends Freedmen's Association in Philadelphia (a Quaker organization), Shaeffer received financial backing for the school. In 1896 Booker T. Washington molded the program to one that would emphasize technical training for blacks. A 185-acre farm was purchased as the school's campus in 1905. In 1934 the Montgomery County School Board began its management of the school. CII was converted in 1947 to a regional high school for blacks, and closed in 1966 when the local schools were integrated.
Scope and Content Information
The CII materials consist of photocopied historical documents about the school, its history, and the alumni association. Many of the materials are from the Edgar A. Long papers (Long served as principal of the school from 1905 to 1924), and include Long's handwritten drafts of lectures, writings, speeches, sermons, and lessons. Also included are copies of the 1902-03 and 1925-26 catalogs and the 1908 annual report. "Poems for Children and Letters," compiled by Nerissa Long Milton, "Married Life" compiled by Dora E.W. Spratt, and "Art Letters and Poetry of Audrey Long Whitlock", compiled by Amanda De Hart, are part of the alumni records. The bulk of the material was compiled under the title "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History and the Edgar A. Long Papers, 1866-1986" by Mrs. Amanda Edwin De Hart, archivist and historian for the CII alumni association.
For additional Christiansburg Industrial Institute resources available online or in print, see:
Digital Images
"A Century of Contribution" Curatorial Advisory Committee photographs from meeting April 4, 2000 (pdf)
Louretta Wimberly: African American Preservation Alliance photographs from HUM 4414-3040, April 3, 2000 presentation (pdf)
Manuscript Resources at Other Universities
Finding aid for the Papers of John F. Banks, 1910-1959, Special Collections, Johnson Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Afro-American Resources in Virginia: A Guide to Manuscripts, Michael Plunkett, ed., University Press of Virginia, 1994.
"Henrietta James" (CII Graduate) in the History of the American Negro Index.
Presentations and Websites
Christiansburg Industrial, Incorporated
Christiansburg Industrial Alumni Association
In the News
"Symposium Examines Equity in Virginia Schools," Spectrum Sept. 17, 1999: 1
CI fund drive under way, Spectrum, April 20, 1995
CI topic of TV show, Spectrum, Feb. 11, 1999: 4.
Other Resources
Fariello, M. Anna, ed., A Vistion of Education: Selected Writings of Edgar A. Long, Christiansburg VA: Christiansburg Institute, 2003. Available at Special Collections: Spec Large LC2852 .C529 L66 2003.
Fariello, M. Anna, "On a Shallow Foundation of Freedom: Building the Campus of the Christiansburg Institute," Smithfield Review VI (2002): 38-70. Available in Newman Library and in Special Collections: F217 .B6 S64.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to subject matter.
Contents List
- "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History and the Edgar A. Long Papers," pp. 1-209. 1866-1986 (Box-folder 1-1)
- "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History and the Edgar A. Long Papers" pp. 210-424 and appendixes. 1866-1986 (Box-folder 1-2)
- "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History: A Century of Service to Youth Ends 1966," by Amanda Edwin De Hart. 1989 (Box-folder 1-3)
- "Christiansburg Institute History: Photographs," compiled by Amanda Edwin De Hart. 1989 (Box-folder 1-4)
- "Catalog of the Christiansburg Industrial Institute, Cambria, Va.," and "Annual Report of the Christiansburg Industrial Institute." 1902-1903, 1908 (Box-folder 1-5)
- "The Christiansburg Industrial Institute Twenty-Eighth Annual Catalogue." 1925-1926 (Box-folder 1-6)
- "Annual Alumni Catalogue: Day School and Night School Graduates," partial [lists CII alumni.] 1898, 1891-1925 (Box-folder 1-7)
- "Married Life: A Blessing to the Truly Married," arranged [compiled] by Mrs. Dora E.W. Spratt. 1893, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- "Poems for Children and Letters," by Nerissa Long Milton. 1986, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
- "Art Letters and Poetry from Audrey Long Whitlock" [compiled] by Amanda Edwin De Hart. 1972-1990 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Articles about the history of CII; photographs of collages of CII alumni. 1991 (Box-folder 1-11)
- "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History and the Edgar A. Long Papers," 1866-1986. (Box-folder 2-1)
- "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History: Part II: A Collection of Items," 1989. (Box-folder 2-2)
- "Christiansburg Industrial Institute History: Part III: Photographs," 1989. (Box-folder 2-3)
- Christiansburg Industrial Institute, The Twenty-Eighth Annual Catalog (photocopy), 1925-1926. (Box-folder 2-4)
- Poetry from Raleigh Randolph, 1984-1996. (Box-folder 2-5)
- "Official Program and Souvenir Book, Christiansburg Institute," (first reunion), July 1-3, 1977. (Box-folder 2-6)
- Christiansburg Industrial Institute Reunion photograph album, July 1-3, 1977. (Box-folder 2-7)
- "Welcome to Christiansburg Institute 2nd Reunion," July 4-6, 1980. (Box-folder 2-8)
- Scrapbooks. (Box 3)